Joseph Cornell
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
- Diaries, 1941-1973, Series 3:; (boxes 6-10; 5 linear feet)
  - Diary Entries, 1941-1972, 3.1:
    - June1954 (Box 6, Folder 29)
      Includes references to: reading Ondine by Giraudoux, appreciation of Ondine experiences via Cerrito-Fourth Ave., "coincidence" of working on Dovecote and listening to "Somnambula," new collage application to Gozzoli "Prince," Berenice and GC 44 experiences, refurbishing the yellow Vermeer box, and Pink Girl and Donkey on Corona billboard; as well as commentary on the relationship between diary keeping and box construction.
    - July1954 (Box 6, Folder 30)
      Includes references to: modus operandi of listening to music, burning desire to reach young people, more flexible modus operandi of images vs. objects (boxes), C.S., and leg ailment.
    - August1954 (Box 6, Folder 31)
      Includes references to: "Maria" brochure, Berlioz, Beethoven, Little Dancer dream of GC 44; commentary on the creation process and the finished product.
    - September1954 (Box 6, Folder 32)
      Includes references to: Sun box, experiences in browsing, three-dimensional work and other projects in progress, Cockatoo box, Corona girl and donkey, windfall of scrapbook material from Brousseau, Juan Gris, family tension, and Malibran period.
    - October1954 (Box 6, Folder 33)
      Includes references to: Ann - a memory by De Quincey, bird boxes, city wanderings of Whitman period, Dovecote Colombier, Julie Lespinasse, E.D. and inspiration for the Dovecote series, "harvesting" in secondhand bookstores, "warm atmosphere" of cellar workroom, Nicolas Berdyaer's Dream and Reality, and "explorations" such as Cerrito, Pasta, and Malibran.
    - November1954 (Box 6, Folder 34)
      Includes references to: Malibran, "Corona house," sense of the past in the present, and his frustration with the medium of boxes.
    - December1954 (Box 6, Folder 35)
      Includes references to: mobile effects in Bird Boxes, smile of counter girl (E.D. type), and "Night Songs" exhibition at Egan Gallery in 1950.
    - January1955 (Box 6, Folder 36)
      Includes references to: Schumann's Spring Symphony, Andromeda, "Aviary" follow-up, Zizi's canary, Lesson Sermon, and the Iolas Gallery; as well as reflections on diary keeping.
    - February1955 (Box 6, Folder 37)
      Includes references to: "Maria" brochure, Tilly Losch, Vermeer, Fourth Avenue, Lucile Grahn, making film with Stan Brakhage, and "Little Malibran" sighting.
    - March1955 (Box 6, Folder 38)
      Includes references to: Lucile Grahn, Berenice feeling, Cerrito "findings," Corona backyards seen from the El, GC 44 bike rides, Hotel de L'Etoile, Hotel Du Bon Port, Andromeda, and "Le Caliph of Bagdad" cockatoo box (for Boieledieu-Adam); as well as reflections on diary keeping.
    - April1955 (Box 6, Folder 39)
      Includes references to: "Hotel Andromeda," Eluard sparking, Carlotta Grisi, Einstein, Corona houses, Cerrito popping off the page of an old Harvard catalogue on theater, working in cellar with urge for town, and reaction to panorama over Flushing Creek.
    - May1955 (Box 6, Folder 40)
      Includes references to: Hotel Andromeda, Juan Gris Cockatoo, sorting and preparing "Maria" brochures, Vermeer boxes, "secrets of childhood" box, and dismantling of Parmigianino box; as well as dried flowers.
    - June1955 (Box 6, Folder 41)
      Includes references to: "Paul and Virginia" box, work on Cerrito, Lucile Grahn white wall box, and "foreign feeling about boxes."
    - July1955 (Box 6, Folder 42)
      Includes references to: "Eurydice" at counter, Pasta cockatoo, preoccupation with "Bel Canto Pet," Cerrito filing, exhibition at Stable Gallery, Gwen Van Dam, "owl for Gwendoline," Motherwell call, and Lesson Sermon.
    - August1955 (Box 6, Folder 43)
      Includes references to: gallery presentation of Vermeer boxes, metamorphosis of Soap Bubble Set, Hurricane Connie and its aftermath, "Nostalgia of the Sea," Room 43 experience of first meeting Gwen, compartment work in jetsam pharmacy, assembly of "L'Humeur Vagabonde," Sheree North, visit by Stan Brakhage, and "Midsummer Portrait" scenario.
    - September1955 (Box 6, Folder 44)
      Includes references to: cellar work, "The Typewriter" (play starring Gwen Van Dam), windfall of books and LPs, Durer box, Jeanne's box, Parmigianino girl, Gwen's planet box, "Dien Bien Phu," "Cote d'Emerande," domestic tension, GC 44, Third Avenue El project with Stan Brakhage, and Lucile Grahn.
    - October1955 (Box 6, Folder 45)
      Includes references to: sun boxes, Dukas box, encounter with Botticellian girl, Fanny Cerrito, and "Eurydice" in Bickford's.
    - November1955 (Box 6, Folder 46)
      Includes references to: the urge to do more with color, Pasta cockatoo, GC 44 College Point diner experience, home tension, film shooting in Union Square, Spanish teenagers evoking Raquel Meller and Malibran, Suzanne Miller, Chopin sparking, and "The Lamp-Maker."
    - December1955 (Box 6, Folder 47)
      Includes references to: talks with Suzanne and evocation of old buildings from William Whitman days.
    - January1956 (Box 6, Folder 48)
      Includes references to: butterfly collage of Jackie, Whitney Colombier, Haydn's "Lark" Quartet, working on film Aviary, apricot fee, "Lampmaker" parrot, and Little Durer compartment.
    - February1956 (Box 6, Folder 49)
      Includes references to: 1940 Malibran extravaganzas, disappearance of Third Avenue El, cellar jotting, generous payment for "Christmas Research" for Vogue, golden days of gallery trotting, appreciation of stars, frustration with "explorations," Mahler #7, and Morgan Library.
    - March1956 (Box 6, Folder 50)
      Includes references to: apricot fee, orange dahlia (for Sheree North), Delacroix, Vermeer, check from Stable Gallery, film work with Rudy Burckhardt, reviewing box of Cerrito material, working on bird boxes, Lois Smith sparking, and dream about Andover.
    - April1956 (Box 6, Folder 51)
      Includes references to: creative listening, "correspondence" between Satie music and bird box, Portraits of Women, Cocteau clipping file, Acadian Songs and Dance, and Julie de Lespinasse.
    - May1956 (Box 6, Folder 52)
      Includes references to: Ondine, Linda Howard, Satie, Antiques Fair, Pasta experience in Woolworth's, Children's Room (NYPL), Rilke, and Fanny Cerrito "exploration"; as well as commentary on diary keeping.
    - June1956 (Box 6, Folder 53)
      Includes references to: Suzanne Miller and film Fable for Fountains, Satie music, bus to College Point, GC 44, Schubert #3, lamp maker parrot, and Grahn.
    - July1956 (Box 6, Folder 54)
      Includes references to: Allegra Kent, Taglioni's "Le Papillon," new Lucile Grahn box, Fifene experience, cellar mood vs. city wanderlusting, Cockatoo for Pasta, seeing the film La Strada, Allegra box, and "Le Retour de la Sylphide."
    - August1956 (Box 6, Folder 55)
      Includes references to: Joseph Weitz visit to cellar, Lois Smith, Portraits of Women, Frumkin visit, Etchika Choureau (French actress), evocation of Lawrence homestead and GC 44, phenomenon of overemotionalism, Chopin "Etudes," Wanamaker's demolition, Bird Room project, "find" in biography of Merrimee about 12 year-old ballerina, Sylvia Lijou, clue to Cerrito experience, and Pasta and cabbages.
    - September1956 (Box 6, Folder 56)
      Includes references to: box for Holderlin, "grand tour" of the book stalls and "trouvaille" of three old French books, Hotel Salamander, Hotel Valencia, many Cerrito NYC experiences, and GC 44.
    - October1956 (Box 6, Folder 57)
      Includes references to: bike ride, Hotel Valencia alias Salamander, Grahn, St. Saens Egyptian piano concerto, intangible "visitations," and "holidays of the mind."
    - November1956 (Box 6, Folder 58)
      Includes references to: work on collage, Jackie, "Alpine Game," film work with Rudy Burckhardt, and work on Aviary film.
    - December1956 (Box 6, Folder 59)
      Includes references to: reminder of girl and donkey on poster in Corona Houses folio, dream of Nyack, Jackie Lane (English starlet), new variant of Forgotten Game, Hummingbird collage, "Little Malibran," "Andromeda," and difficulty of reaching people through exhibiting art work in galleries.
    - January-February1957 (Box 7, Folder 1)
      Includes references to: constellations, Helen Keller on TV, revision of sun image box, work on new cube box, Rose Fried (art dealer), Pepys sun diary sparking, Melissa Hayden in "The Nutcracker," Delacroix warmth, and Debussy.
    - March-April1957 (Box 7, Folder 2)
      Includes references to: Bird Box, consolation of Liszt, cellar working, Medici Princess, new kind of collage, sparkings from clippings, appreciation of Jackie butterfly collage, new owl box, dream of Broadway during William Whitman days, cellar carpentry on Medici boxes, Pinturicchio Boy, reading of "Ruth" by Claire Bloom, Dukas, Pasta's Parrot, new night skies and small Colombier, Durer box, new "spirit-level" Soap Bubble Set, and creative reading in Night Songs folder.
    - May-June1957 (Box 7, Folder 3)
      Includes references to: Pasta Parrot, Grahn, Claire Bloom, Jackie collages, Sun Box, diary entries, increasing difficuly of overcharged emotions, feeling for reaching young people through art work, Chamber Street fee, grace de fee teenager, and the new Vermeer girl.
    - July-August1957 (Box 7, Folder 4)
      Includes references to: Judy Tyler, Vermeer girl, Oswaldo box "Il Signor il Sole," Sheree North, Judy Tyler box #2 "Suzy's Sun," and Schumann.
    - September-October1957 (Box 7, Folder 5)
      Includes references to: fee d'or, Jackie butterfly, "Little Loredana," sailor's wife inspiration for Humeur Vagabonde, Gerard de Nerval, "atelier working," and working through tedium; as well as commentary on diary keeping.
    - November-December1957 (Box 7, Folder 6)
      Includes references to: Pasta, "Fable" film, impact of last movement of Gerschwin's Concerto in F, neighborhood "teener" as "little Cerrito," inordinate love of city, and appreciation of film work done; as well as commentaries on boxes and scribblings.
    - January-February1958 (Box 7, Folder 7)
      Includes references to: Gozzoli, GC 44 sorting, Pasta and cabbages, new global box called Trade Winds, the impact of familiar faces, breaking the gallery "slavery," and feeling of emptiness in readying for Stable exhibit.
    - March1958 (Box 7, Folder 8)
      Includes references to: scribblings, "Le Dame Blanche" of Boieldieu, new series of Colombier, depression about Robert and others like him, the image of the apricot fee, the maiden with the crossed hands, sylphide hunt in photo magazines, dream of Mary Baker Eddy, Union Square shootings with Rudy, and film The Children's Party.
    - April1958 (Box 7, Folder 9)
      Includes references to: the maiden with the crossed hands, former obsession with church attendance, Dukas "search," carpentry on new compass boxes, Little Durer box, beautiful "trouvaille" on 4th Avenue, Judy Tyler, "Le Seigneur des Enseignes" collage, Rose Fried, sense of "audience" to reach, and B. Voohr.
    - May-June1958 (Box 7, Folder 10)
      Includes references to: "Hotel de L'Etoile," fresh views of Seurat, Bonnard model, Joan Collins in "Land of the Pharoahs," being in collage mood and difficulty of achieving spontaneity in boxes, rabbit collage, Mary Welch, and new reworking of cockatoo and fish collage.
    - July1958 (Box 7, Folder 11)
      Includes references to: Pinturicchio Boy, Medici Princess, a Pasta Parrot off to C.H. Ford, Rubber Mouse King (one of Robert Cornell's creations), Matta, Vermeer girl, break-up of J. Tyler "mourning," box carpentry for new Moon Chart with Portuguese glasses, and much "traveling" in thoughts.
    - August1958 (Box 7, Folder 12)
      Includes references to: love for own work and obsession with boxes, Sheree North working, Gerard de Nerval, GC 44, "Miss Melon," star boxes, feeling of being close to a "world of Novalis," American Gothic, Parmigianino, refurbished Whitney Annual "Orion" which became Andromeda, and the girl with folded hands.
    - September1958 (Box 7, Folder 13)
      Includes references to: refurbishing Durer box, artificiality of boxes, attic working with Dennis, Oswaldo inspiration, and how little of real life gets into boxes.
    - October-November1958 (Box 7, Folder 14)
      Includes references to: Serafina's Garden shooting, Nostalgia of the Sea, Sailor's Children, Linda Vandal, France Nuyen (actress) in The World of Suzie Wong on Broadway, swan collage, Little Durer waiting to go into Whitney Annual, Jenny Jones in Love Letters, Juan Gris "frog serenade," and "revelations" peculiar to work in boxes.
    - December1958 (Box 7, Folder 15)
      Includes references to: hunger for human touch on Main Street, France Nuyen "Voyageur's" Hotel, personal feeling of working with old wood for boxes, Sun Box, College Point diner, GC 44, diversity of experience, Beguin collage, new Sand Fountain with mirror effect, seeing Allegra Kent in Hildebrand's, Shirley MacLaine "exploration," mail to Aaron Siskind, E.D. "illumination," new Hotel Colombier, Brereton reading, and jottings.
    - January1959 (Box 7, Folder 16)
      Includes references to: Brereton's "French Poets," "Berenice tenement," gulls for Grahn, Forgotten Game, Mylene Demongeot (French actress), Global Parrot, and Ondine "exploration"; reflections on process of box making and final product of boxes.
    - February1959 (Box 7, Folder 17)
      Includes references to: collage "headquarters" (8th Ave + 43rd St), seeing France Nuyen walking up 8th Ave, Debussy coming to life, dream with strong flavor of GC 44, fees aux lapins, sister phenomena of being asleep and awake, Ridgewood bus ride of a year ago, "la fee aux tenebres," doll box, new Sand Fountain box, and cellar working with an "atelier" feeling.
    - March1959 (Box 7, Folder 18)
      Includes references to: Renata Scotto debut as "the young Malibran," Berlioz sparking, two cascades sand box for Paul Valery, Claire Bloom, Debussy world of "Pelleas," cellar stalemate, creative filing, and sparkings from objects and brochures.
    - April1959 (Box 7, Folder 19)
      Includes references to: routine meals as "mystique d'appetit," Sun Box for Judy, urge for presenting projects to the young, Duchamp, Claire Bloom, Mylene Demongeot, new "Scarlatti Parrot," new type of "Colombier," dream about Raquel Meller 1925, and resumption of collage work after months of dormancy.
    - May1959 (Box 7, Folder 20)
      Includes references to: dream of France Nuyen, Judy Tyler Sun, Elsa Martinelli box, Vermeer, changing the Scarlatti Parrot #2, changed frame of mind about "the past," "The Peering Maiden," preoccupation with Grahn dossier, Duse box, Hotel Pelican, and working on new Dien Bien Phu and Pasta bird box.
    - June1959 (Box 7, Folder 21)
      Includes references to: Ludwig II box, Irving Blum visit, Grahn, and Shirley MacLaine; as well as incomprehensible writings.
    - July1959 (Box 7, Folder 22)
      Includes references to: Shirley MacLaine collage work, Trade Winds box, "slumbering" works, Ristori biography found at Weiser's, Cerrito, Pasta file, catching up the Ondine trail, "Hotel Tudor" Sun Box renamed "Cherubino," appreciation of diverse moods in a single day, Ostend Sun box, L'Humeur Vagabonde '55, Sailor's Children, the "Cherubino" experience, another box in the chain of Space Boxes started for Ferus Gallery, sparking to work with children more, and "ringside" seat by the window in diner.
    - August1959 (Box 7, Folder 23)
      Includes references to: bringing back the feeling of GC 44, Robert's example of courage, brand new compartment box, Demongeot, Gerard de Nerval, Sheree North experience, sailor's children, mother and two children, an obsession to reach people, aftermath writing, Robert's drawing of a horse, "The Candle Lantern" for Shirley MacLaine, and Cerrito as an important kind of technique.
    - September-October1959 (Box 7, Folder 24)
      Includes references to: Edwin Bergman's purchase of his art work, Grahn, Cherubino (sometimes abbreviated as Cher.), Stern collage, inspiration of Magritte's "Empire of Lights," Gwen, Feigen and Jean Wade.
    - November1959 (Box 7, Folder 25)
      Includes references to: trouvaille of Caroline von Gunderode, "second sleeps," Cherubino experience, Valery renewal, Mozart #19, star hotel, Hotel Bon Port, and Irving Blum visit.
    - December1959 (Box 7, Folder 26)
      Includes references to: a dream of Gerard de Nerval, pock-marked girl providing "drama," "the once seen," romantic character of "La Boheme," "angel scribble" episode involving stationery girl, "teener" librarian, Little Durer, review of maiden with the crossed hands, Judy Barsky from Bennington College, Juan Gris, Golding's book on Cubism, and bewilderment over refusal of Xmas gift by counter girl.
    - January1960 (Box 7, Folder 27)
      Includes references to: Cerrito, Rimbaud sparking, Mylene Demongeot, Sheree North, Basch color portrait, death of Albert Camus and a possible Homage, loneliness as being necessary to produce certain phenomena, obsessive desire to do an "In Memoriam" with boxes, sparking to get beyond boxes, "L'Ete" sea piece at the Stable Gallery, Pascale Petit (for Cherubino), maiden with clasped hands, Vermeer girl, Constable's sketches and their implications for his own work, new Andromeda box, and lighted Bird box.
    - February1960 (Box 7, Folder 28)
      Includes references to: "fee aux lapins," lavender fee, rainbow fairy, Cherubino, newly fixed Uccello box, "creative library" supplementing boxes, journals of Delacroix, sources of inspiration, and the drying up of happy hunting grounds.
    - March1960 (Box 7, Folder 29)
      Includes references to: "Coppelia" as an archetype of fragile youth (Jane Fonda type), reminder of E.D. "readymade," Cherubino, Parmigianino #2 (Allegra), cellar working on Andromeda Sand Fountain, interest in all types of "teeners," and the "Kneeling Maiden"; as well as commentary on boxes and naturalness of work.
    - April1960 (Box 7, Folder 30)
      Includes references to: Debussy file, Cherubino and her boyfriend, "M.M." experience, Voohr collage, Beatrix collage, Fischer Beer's experience of last fall, remembering "Nymph-light," and first attempt at recalling Daphne Dream of 2/23/59.
    - May1960 (Box 7, Folder 31)
      Includes references to: blooming of M.M., fee aux lapins, phone call from Ed Bergman (collector), and gently drawing in the net of memory "before it fades."
    - June1960 (Box 7, Folder 32)
      Includes references to: set of dreams, Juan Gris, Debussy guitar music, remembrance of encounter with fee aux lapins, Carlotta experience, Yvette Mimieux, Feigen visit, "Hotel des Etrangers" box, and missed opportunities to reach young people because of home situation.
    - July1960 (Box 7, Folder 33)
      Includes references to: Betty Biehn experience, Caroline von Gunderode, the curious "Carlotta" turn in the Cerubino experience, and "teeners."
    - August1960 (Box 7, Folder 34)
      Includes references to: going through Vermeer books, starting tiny sun box, picking out Hartley Coleridge from garage overflow of books, "creative browsing," remembered joy of a particular find, Little Malibran in diary notes and connection to new Cherubino experience, and "Maria" brochure; as well as commentary on diary keeping.
    - September1960 (Box 7, Folder 35)
      Includes references to: Debussy's obsession with objects, Little Durer file, scraping new Durer from Judy Tyler discard, GC 44, Mozart horn concerto, and Dutch Still Life.
    - October1960 (Box 7, Folder 36)
      Includes references to: Cinderella in Fisher Beer's, coincidence of bird sunset collage and tree catching last sun in storm setting, collage shopping, the "light of other days," the "once seen," Cherubino, being waited on by Cassiopeia, and jaunt to College Point.
    - November1960 (Box 7, Folder 37)
      Includes references to: new Grand Hotel de l'Observatoire, GC 44 Floral Still Life, experiences of Cherubino, lack of feeling for working on boxes, scribblings in the small hours, and the "in and out" of daily demands.
    - December1960 (Box 7, Folder 38)
      Includes references to: the Whitney Annual, William Whitman days of wandering, difficulty of catching multi-colored experience with "cataloging," glass cutting, attic review, regret over piece let go to Feigen, "Portraits of Youth," Val, Suzanne Miller, E.D. flavoring in cellar, and Debussy "Preludes."
    - January-February1961 (Box 7, Folder 39)
      Includes references to: GC 44 experiences, the feeling in acquiring things, Hydra (Durer) plate, Elizabeth Moran (helper), M.M. (not Marilyn), Le Grande Meaulnes (by Alain Fournier), blond "teener" in "Il Sole" store, "fee aux lapins" experience again, speaking to Cherubino for the first time since refusal of gift, and finding little of the glow of former times in review of Ondine; as well as commentaries on art work and scribbling.
    - March1961 (Box 7, Folder 40)
      Includes references to: futility of ever getting down experience on paper, "Jenny Jones" schoolgirl on bus, Cerrito/Ondine thread, postcard from Matta, "missing child" collage, Crystal Tower, and the little "all or nothing" dramas of the commonplace.
    - April1961 (Box 7, Folder 41)
      Includes references to: Mylene, Pamela Bianco, the endlessly mysterious processes of the mind and workings of the spirit, renewing acquaintances with Barr, Pernas, and Porter from the Museum of Modern Art, fee encounter, "Deer in Landscape," Judy and Amy working in cellar, and the "figurehead" collage.
    - May1961 (Box 7, Folder 42)
      Includes references to: first church attendance in months, air crash in Africa, Cherubino experience, sparking of "Old Fashioned Flowers," book browsing, Pascale Petit, Ferus "space box," Juan Gris #7, "The Iris Nest" collage, Tina (fairy princess) collage, Mylene file, and cellar workings with Basch theme color portrait.
    - June1961 (Box 7, Folder 43)
      Includes references to: "The Pleides," recollection of first meeting Gwen in 1955, and gratitude for dove pipes from Gwen; as well as commentary on diaries.
    - July1961 (Box 7, Folder 44)
      Includes references to: Coulter girl, Cherubino, Alfred Goldsmith dream, "angel scribbler," Mahler #4, Wordsworth's insights into nature, feelings of inadequacy, a "Book of Hours," Jackie collage, new Space Box, and Diana collage.
    - August1961 (Box 7, Folder 45)
      Includes references to: often needless indulgence in magazines, bewilderingly diverse worlds being opened up by a certain young miss, childhood scene "pushing through," sparking for a December show combining Cherubino and Cassiopeia, and David Herbert visit.
    - September1961 (Box 7, Folder 46)
      Includes references to: being waited on by Cassiopeia (often abbreviated as Cass.), array of material for another Aviary, The Balcony (play), M.M. and her sister throng, collage browsing, and the Bickford waitress becoming "the maiden."
    - October1961 (Box 7, Folder 47)
      Includes references to: Cass., E.B. Ward, too much "cataloging," the death of Maya Deren, recurrent images from old Fourth Ave browsing days, Antiques Fair, "corrected" sense of people, Assemblage exhibit, compartment boxes, and so-called Humeur Vagabonde series.
    - November1961 (Box 7, Folder 48)
      Includes references to: Crystal Cage Palace, Schubert, Mahler, Goethe, stars at midnight evoking Cass. and Cher., and Robert's beautiful mood at home.
    - December1961 (Box 7, Folder 49)